Muhammad Shakeeb Alam Red Hat Certified Architect

mmshakeeb@hotmail.com

+92 345 2326980

Karachi, Pakistan 🤵

linkedin.com/in/shakeeb-alam-83252325a (in

credly.com/users/shakeeb-alam.00000000 @

HR Department,



Dear Hiring Team,

I am writing to express my keen interest in cloud and systems domains. As a highly motivated and accomplished professional with more than 9 years of experience in banking sector, with a passion for designing and implementing cutting-edge core system, bigdata and cloud solution, I would bring my tenacity and penchant for success to your organization. As such, here are the main area of expertise you may talk about: OpenShift, Advance Cluster Management and Cluster Security, Containerization, Kubernetes and its security, 24/7 High Availability Clustering using Pacemaker, corosync, HAProxy, Glusterfs, SAN Storage, Ceph Storage, OpenShift Data foundation, Virtualization using RHVM, Performance Tunning, Cloud Infrastructure with Openstack, Automation with Ansible, Linux Server management, DevOps, CI/CD Pipeline.

As an accomplished Redhat Architect, I have played a pivotal role in crafting robust cloud strategies and executing successful OpenShift/Kubernetes implementation at United Bank limited. Throughout this journey, I have led this project from designing phase to implementation. My extensive background in cloud technologies, coupled with my strong problem-solving abilities, has consistently resulted in optimized performance, enhanced security, reduced risk and concerns.

In addition, my thesis research on Kubernetes network security under the supervision of Prof. Dr. Hasan Jamil Syed, leads to identifies emerging ideas, discoveries of security threats, developing effective defence strategies, threat intelligence gathering, evaluating security tools and technologies.

I am eager to join a team that embraces creativity and fosters an environment where employees can thrive and contribute meaningfully.

Thank you for considering my application. I look forward to the possibility of contributing to the continued success of your organization as the Senior Manager. Please find my contact information above should you wish to reach out to schedule a meeting.

Sincerely,

Muhammad Shakeeb Alam, **RHCA**

Muhammad Shakeeb Alam
• +92-345-2326980
• mmshakeeb@hotmail.com
• DOB 01-july-1992



Professional Summary

I am a Redhat Certified Architect Level 1, possess a wide range of skills in Cloud, Linux, Bigdata Hadoop Administration, Clustering, Automation, Virtualization and Containerization. I have more than 8 years of experience working on Linux based environment. I am committed to finding innovative solutions to a variety of IT problems, such as security, automation and technical troubleshooting. I can offer your organization exemplary support with system and cloud security, administration, increased system performance and high availability.

Education

FAST - National University of Computer & Emerging Sciences | MS in Computer Network and Security (2024)
Institute of Business and Technology | BS in Software Engineering (2015)
Gov. Degree College Malir Cantt | Intermediate in Computer Science (2010)
St. Francis. School | Matriculation in Computer Science (2008)

Certification

Red	Hat® Certified Architect (RHCA® Level 1) Certification ID: 170-269-799
	Red Hat® Certified Specialist in OpenShift Multi Cluster Management
	Red Hat® Certified Specialist in OpenStack Cloud Infrastructure
	Red Hat® Certified Specialist in Containers and Kubernetes
	Red Hat® Certified Specialist in High Availability Clustering
	Red Hat® Certified Specialist in Open Shift Administration
	Red Hat® Certified Engineer (RHCE®)
	Red Hat® Certified System Administrator (RHCSA®)
Certified Kubernetes Administrator (CKA)	
Certified Kubernetes Security Specialist (CKS)	
Certified Kubernetes Application Developer (CKAD)	

Experience

• United Bank Limited (8 years)

Aptech Education Center

HDP Certified Administrator (HDPCA)

Diploma in Information System Management (DISM)

RVP /Manager System Administration | 2024—Present AVP /Manager System Administration | 2022—2023 OG-I /Senior System Administrator | 2018—2021 OG-II /Linux System Administrator | 2016—2018

Cloud Administration

- Perform Day1 and Day2 OpenShift operations.
- Manage 10 Nodes x 3 OpenShift Cluster Platforms (OCP) for Infinity.
- Manage 8 Nodes x 3 OpenShift Cluster for IBM Cloud Pak for Integration (CP4I)

- Manage 3 Nodes K8's cluster for Kubeflow.
- Manage fleet of OCP Clusters in Single Window using Automate Cluster Management (ACM).
- Segregate network segments for DMZ and internal traffic using OCP network policies
- Design network rules for restricting traffic between the pods.
- Managing the secret and config map to ensure user have specific privileges to access.
- Reserve and limit application compute capacity.
- Manage application scaling to meet increased demand according the compute capacity.
- Integration of OpenShift with different identity provider such as OpenLDAP, Active directory and RHSSO.
- Secure end-to-end communication of routes and services.
- Mange user, groups, service-account, roles, cluster-roles and role-bindings.
- Ensure proper security context constraint (SCC's) is assigned to control permission of pods.
- Ensure that no privileged application is running.
- Ensure that all application and images have labels, selectors and tags.
- Manage placement of pods with affinity, anti-affinity, taint, tolerance rules.
- Manage cluster and project resource quotas.
- Design template to parameterized and processed set of objects upon creation of project by user.
- Mange cluster and operators upgrade.
- Mange and configure storage class with different external provider.
- Customise storage classes.
- Manage ODF storage quotas and permissions.
- Manage and provision Persistent Storage volumes for block and file-based data.
- Perform backup and restore of block and file volumes.
- Perform backup and restore of etcd.
- Mange volume snapshots and clones.
- Manage object bucket claims and access object storage.
- Manage internal image registry and interact with many different registries.
- Implement images using Podman
- Define OCP Governance policies using ACM.
- Scan and detect OCP vulnerabilities using Advance Cluster Security (ACS).
- Develop RHACS policy to prevent deployment of vulnerable images
- OCP Compliance Management using ACS.
- OCP Risk Management using ACS.
- Monitoring OCP using Grafana and OCP Dashboard.
- Establishing CI/CD pipeline for automated deployment.
- Integrate CI/CD pipeline with RHACM

System Administration

- Maintain bank's colossus system in peak performance.
- Managing 15 Node Cluster of Hortonworks (HDP 3.4).
- Experience in deploying and managing the multi-node development and production Hadoop cluster with different Hadoop components (HIVE, PIG, SQOOP, OOZIE, HBASE, ZOOKEEPER) using Hortonworks Ambari.
- Manage and troubleshooting of more than 300 productions and tdl Linux servers.
- Manage more than 200 production users by providing proper profiles and discretionary Access Control.
- Manage and configure of LDAP users and replication of configuring on standby site.
- Manage and configure the DNS server on rhel7 with replication at standby site.
- Kernel level performance tuning experience on production server.
- Managing partition and used lym for dynamically extending and reducing on real time.
- Troubleshooting and analysis of the systems logs for the root cause of the problem, whether it may be for hardware issue or software issue.
- Kick installation on multiple servers at a time.
- Creates Linux Virtual Machines using VMware esxi, red hat virtualization, ovm.
- Installation of Apache and IBM WebSphere servers.
- Configure Apache virtual host, access restriction and tls security.
- Prepared the document of every configuration and migration.

- Working on VNX EMC, Oracle and Hitachi storages
- Create LUNs using lym in iSCSi Target server and setting up the client initiator.
- Backup and restore using veritas net backup.
- An excellent team player has very good relationships with the various application Teams and the Infrastructure teams.
- Provided 24/7 technical support to Production and development environments
- Provided technical support by troubleshooting Day-to-Day issues with various servers
- Documented all setup procedures and System related Policies
- Shared knowledge with juniors.

Big Data Hadoop Administration

- Hands on experience in installation, configuration, supporting and managing Hadoop Clusters using Horton works.
- Strong knowledge in configuring High Availability for Name Node, HBase, Hive and Resource Manager.
- Hadoop Cluster capacity planning, performance tuning, cluster Monitoring, Troubleshooting.
- Secured Hadoop Cluster by implementing Kerberos with MIT Kerberos and One way trust with Active Directory.
- Making Hadoop cluster ready for development team working.
- Hands on experience in analyzing Log files for Hadoop and eco system services and finding root cause.

High Availability and Load Balancing Solution.

- Experience in implementing High Availability Solutions using REDHAT pacemaker cluster.
- Active/Active High Availability Pacemaker Cluster with GFS2, Active/Passive Cluster with DRBD, configure
 esxi based and libvirt base stonith /fencing along with the quorum Configure and Manage logical volumes in a
 clustered environment, configuration of cluster logging and monitoring.
- Configure the active/active files system with glusterfs file system
- Configure the HTTP Load Balancer with haproxy

Automation and infrastructure management product

- Using Ansible automation create playbook that run ad hoc Ansible commands which helps to automate the management and deployment of application.
- Performed system update to fix the (IBM big fix) and (Nexpose) scan vulnerabilities and to maintain optimum system availability and usability.

Security

- Implementation of security hardening with firewalld and SElinux.
- Designed the CIS based kickstart file for hardening the linux installation.
- Implement Kerberos for secure user authentication
- Implement 2 factor authentication on all servers to mitigate the risk
- Configure system auditing
- Manage system login security using pluggable authentication modules
- Configure AIDE to monitor critical system files.
- Fulcrum Consulting Services Company (Deputed at United Bank Limited as System Admin Engineer Contractual) (2015 2016)
- Net Eyes Cyber Solution (Database Developer) (1 year)